{"tossups": [{"question": "In this U.S. state, a team of death row inmates played baseball as the \"Alston's All-Stars\" to postpone their own execution date. This state's Fort Laramie served as a staging ground for army offensives during the Great Sioux [[SOOH]] Wars of the 1870s. While a territory, this modern state became the first to allow women to vote in its elections, leading to its nickname, the \"Equality State\". For ten points, name this state that, since 1890, has been governed from Cheyenne.", "answer": "<b><u>Wyoming</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A contingent of this European people populated the Haitian city of Cazale [[kah-SAL]] after they betrayed Napoleon's troops. Over 20,000 officers and other intelligentsia of these people were murdered by the NKVD in the Katyn [[kah-TEEN]] Forest Massacre. With Hungarian Michael Kovats [[KOH-vach]], a nobleman of this nationality named Casimir Pulaski [[poo-WAH-skee]] reformed the American Cavalry Corps. For ten points, name these people who's country was invaded on September 1, 1939 to begin World War Two.", "answer": "<b><u>Pole</u></b>s (or <b><u>Polish</u></b> People; accept <b><u>Polish</u></b>-Americans; accept <b><u>Polacy</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Transnational Federal Government was formed in 2004 in this nation, which was led by Siad Barre [[SEE-add BAR-reh]] from 1969 until 1991. An American response to civil war in this nation turned disastrous when two Black Hawk helicopters were shot down. During the 2000s, this country was considered the home base of many pirates raiding shipping near the Gulf of Aden. For ten points, name this war-torn nation on the horn of Africa, once divided into British and Italian colonies.", "answer": "<b><u>Somalia</u></b> (accept Federal Republic of <b><u>Somalia</u></b>; or Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka <b><u>Soomaaliya</u></b>; or Jumh\u016briyah as-<b><u>S\u016bm\u0101l</u></b> al-F\u012bdir\u0101liyah; prompt on \"Somaliland\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The melody from this piece was used as Rhodesia's National Anthem during the 1970s, and was also played for German Olympians during the Cold War. Johannes Brahms quoted this melody in one of his symphonies, and the original composer borrowed the lyrics from a Friedrich Schiller poem. Today, this piece of music is used as the Anthem of Europe, and is the melody of the hymn <em>Joyful, Joyful We Adore Thee</em>. For ten points, name this piece of music, the finale of Beethoven's 9th Symphony.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Ode to Joy</u></b></em> (prompt on \"Beethoven's 9th Symphony\" or equivalents before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Faina Vakhreva was the wife of the ruler of this island, whose adopted brother commanded a panzer division during the Anschluss of Austria. Before moving to this island, its leader created the \"Gannan New Deal,\" where civilians could talk to him at a \"public information desk.\" A ruler of this island arrested the \"Rommel of the East,\" Sun Li-jen, under conspiracy charges during the KMT's White Terror. For ten points, Chiang Ching Kuo and his father Chiang Kai Shek both controlled what East Asian island country?", "answer": "<b><u>Taiwan</u></b> (accept <b><u>Republic of China</u></b>; or <b><u>ROC</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A toxic pool labeled for this blight is shown in a political cartoon where men labelled \"Mr. Careless\" and \"Anti-Vaccinationist\" fall off a cliff titled \"Misinformation.\" During the Siege of Fort Pitt, Governor-General Jeffrey Amherst oversaw the gift of several blankets infected with this disease to opposing Native Americans. Edward Jenner inoculated people against, for ten points, what disease that was eradicated in the 1970s?", "answer": "<b><u>Smallpox</u></b> (accept <b><u>Variola</u></b> Major; or <b><u>Variola</u></b> Minor)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This league's color barrier was broken in 1947 by Japanese-American Wataru Misaka. A coach in this league, Steve Kerr, came under fire in 2020 due to his comments about Hong Kong and the role of the Chinese government. In 2009, the owner of this league's Los Angeles Clippers was sued by former star Elgin Baylor on the grounds of racial discrimination. For ten points, name this league which mourned the death of Kobe Bryant in January 2020.", "answer": "<b><u>N</u></b>ational <b><u>B</u></b>asketball <b><u>A</u></b>ssociation (or <b><u>NBA</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A region predominantly made of these geographical features called \"Al-Ahsa\" is known for producing high-quality <em>bisht</em> cloaks. One of these places, whose name translates to \"Field of Trees,\" was the site of the Oracle of Amon, which confirmed Alexander the Great as Pharaoh of Egypt. The Tuareg confederations used these geographical features as waypoints while on Trans-Saharan trade routes. Siwa in Egypt is an example of, for ten points, what fertile patches of land within deserts?", "answer": "<b><u>Oasis</u></b> (or <b><u>Oases</u></b>; accept specifics like Siwa <b><u>Oasis</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Like William Jennings Bryan, this man won a significant portion of electoral votes in multiple elections without becoming president. This man negotiated an end to the Nullification Crisis with his contemporary, John Calhoun. This Whig negotiated the admission of California into the Union three decades after accomplishing a similar feat with Missouri. For ten points, name this \"Great Compromiser\" from Kentucky.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Clay</u></b> Sr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The site of this city was purchased from the Mississauga by Lord Dorchester, though it remained unsettled until Governor John Graves Sicmoe established the town of York. John Strachan negotiated this town's surrender to the Americans in the War of 1812, after which it was the site of Government House on two occasions before it was moved to another location. William Lyons Mackenzie was the first mayor of this city until he abandoned it to lead the Upper Canada Rebellion. The Canadian National Railway built the CN Tower in, for ten points, which Ontario metropolis?", "answer": "<b><u>Toronto</u></b> (accept <b><u>York</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One ruler of this name became the last British monarch to lead an army in the field at the Battle of Dettingen [[deh-TIN-gehn]]. Robert Walpole became the first British prime minister under a ruler of this name after the South Sea Bubble burst. Another ruler of this name suffered from a mental illness believed to be porphyria [[por-\"FEAR\"-ee-ah]] and was king during the American Revolution. For ten points, give this name of four 18th and 19th-century British monarchs.", "answer": "<b><u>George</u></b> (accept <b><u>George</u></b> I; or <b><u>George</u></b> II; or <b><u>George</u></b> III)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The third-place finisher in this U.S. election year suffered a stroke a year prior to it, leading to his poor performance. The Tertium Quids [[TER-shum KWIDS]] were represented by that man, William H. Crawford, in this election year. This election year saw the House of Representatives swing one man's electoral votes to the eventual winner in order to keep a Tennessee politician from winning office. For ten points, name this election year in which John Quincy Adams defeated Andrew Jackson thanks to the \"corrupt bargain.\"", "answer": "Election of <b><u>1824</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A biography of this ruler was written by Xenophon [[ZEE-noh-fohn]], who described this ruler being raised by a shepherd after his grandfather ordered him killed. According to Herodotus [[heh-ROD-oh-tus]], this king died fighting the Scythian queen Tomyris [[TOM-i-riss]]. A namesake cylinder celebrates this king\u2019s defeat of the Babylonian king Nabonidus [[NAB-o-ni-dus]]. For ten points, name this ruler of the city of Anshan and founder of the Persian Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Cyrus the Great</u></b> (accept <b><u>Cyrus II</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Mehdi Bazargan resigned to protest the beginning of this event, which concluded with the signing of the Algiers Accords. The disastrous Operation Eagle Claw attempted to rescue victims of this event. This crisis ended within minutes of the inauguration of Ronald Reagan as U.S. president, following a 444 day period of imprisonment for its victims. For ten points, identify this diplomatic crisis that began when revolutionary students stormed a U.S. embassy in a Middle Eastern capital.", "answer": "<b><u>Iran Hostage</u></b> Crisis (accept <b><u>Tehran Hostage</u></b> Crisis; accept descriptive answers; prompt on \"Storming of the U.S. Embassy in Tehran\" before \"embassy\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A precursor to this period of history was the wartime Port Royal Experiment. The only two-term leader during this period vetoed much of the legislation that was sent to him, but several bills were overridden by the Radical Republicans. During this period, the Enforcement Act was signed into law by President Ulysses S. Grant to counter the nascent Ku Klux Klan. For ten points, name this period of rebuilding that occurred immediately following the Civil War.", "answer": "<b><u>Reconstruction</u></b> era", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Due to an alleged prophecy given by Jan Hus [[YAHN HOOS]], this man is often depicted with a swan. Scottish artist Joseph Noel Paton depicted this man <em>at Erfurt</em> discovering the doctrine of <em>sola fide</em> [[SOH-luh FEE-deh]]. This man was painted on several occasions by his friend and neighbor, Lucas Cranach [[KRAH-nahk]] the Elder, the court painter to the Elector of Saxony. For ten points, name this theologian and seminal figure in the Protestant Reformation who was often depicted in contemporary art.", "answer": "Martin <b><u>Luther</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "During this project, General Leslie Groves undertook a propaganda campaign to prevent \"loose talk\" by its participants. Despite his acts of treason, Klaus Fuchs [[FYOOKS]] was a key component on this project's development but later served nine years in prison for his actions. Because of his study and understanding of fast neutrons, Robert Oppenheimer was a prime member of this project. For ten points, name this top-secret U.S. project which developed the atomic bomb.", "answer": "<b><u>Manhattan</u></b> Project (accept <b><u>Development of Substitute Materials</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "US army officer Henry Schneider revealed that this company provided a third of all trucks in the Wehrmacht through their Cologne plant which was confiscated in 1941. In the 1920s, this company attempted to set up a free state in Brazil in order to dodge the British monopoly on rubber. While not invented by this company's leader, the assembly line was popularized in the car factories of this company. For ten points, name this American based car company famous for its production of Model T's.", "answer": "<b><u>Ford</u></b> Motor Company", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Following the U.S. Invasion of Grenada, the Edward Seaga-led Labour Party</u></b> <b><u>won every seat in this nation's elections due to boycotts by the People's National</u></b> <b><u>Party. Back to Africa proponent Marcus (+)</u> Garvey was from this island nation, which saw multiple \"Maroon Wars\" against the British government. The destruction of Port (*) </b>Royal by a 17th-century earthquake led to the founding of, for ten points, which Caribbean nation's capital of Kingston?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Jamaica</u></b> (or <b><u>Jumieka</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The so-called \"Land Pirate,\" John Murrell, faced allegations of starting one of</u></b> <b><u>these events along the Mississippi River in a namesake \"Excitement.\" The testimony</u></b> <b><u>of George Wilson and Joe LaRoche quashed another of these events planned by a man</u></b> <b><u>known as (+)</u> Telemaque [[teh-leh-MAHK]] in Charleston. One of these events in Southampton, Virginia was suppressed at Belmont (*) </b>Plantation. For ten points, name these uprisings, one of which was led by Nat Turner.", "answer": "<b><u>Slave</u></b> Rebellion (accept equivalents like <b><u>Slave</u></b> Uprising; accept specific answers like \"Denmark <b><u>Vesey</u></b>'s Revolt\" or Nat <b><u>Turner</u></b>'s Revolt; accept \"Enslaved Person\" in place of \"Slave\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This merchant was taken to court after his ship, the</u> </b><em><b><u>Liberty</u></b></em><b><u>, was captured and</u></b> <b><u>he was accused of not paying fees under Townshend Acts. This colonial leader</u></b> <b><u>chaired a committee that demanded the removal of British troops following the (+)</u></b> <b>Boston Massacre. This prot\u00e9g\u00e9 of Samuel Adams served as the first governor of (*) </b>Massachusetts. For ten points, name this president of the Continental Congress who provided the first and largest signature on the Declaration of Independence.", "answer": "John <b><u>Hancock</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The crowning of Joseph Bonaparte led the First Junta [[HOON-tuh]] of this city</u></b> <b><u>to depose Viceroy Hidalgo de Cisneros [[sis-NEH-ros]] as part of the May Revolution.</u></b> <b><u>A women's movement in this city marched in support of those who \"disappeared\"</u></b> <b><u>during the (+)</u> Dirty War. This city's Plaza de Mayo and Casa Rosada presidential palace were bombed by its own air force following a pro-Juan (*) </b>Peron demonstration. The capital of the Viceroyalty of Rio de La Plata was, for ten points, what largest city in Argentina?", "answer": "<b><u>Buenos Aires</u></b> (accept Autonomous City of <b><u>Buenos Aires</u></b>; or Ciudad Aut\u00f3noma de <b><u>Buenos Aires</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this civilization\u2019s archaic period, the Battle of Alalia allowed its</u></b> <b><u>expansion to the Tyrrhenian [[tih-REE-nyen]] Sea. According to legend, twelve cities</u></b> <b><u>from this ancient civilization formed an eponymous (+)</u> league founded by Tachron [[TAH-kron]]. Alleged to have begun during the Iron Age with the Villanova (*) </b>culture, for ten points, what kingdom in ancient Italy was assimilated into Roman society in a series of eponymous wars?", "answer": "<b><u>Etruscan</u></b> civilization (or <b><u>Rasenna</u></b>; or <b><u>Rasna</u></b>; accept <b><u>Tusci</u></b>; accept <b><u>Etrusci</u></b>; accept Roman-<b><u>Etruscan</u></b> Wars; accept <b><u>Tyrrh\u0113noi</u></b> or <b><u>Tyrrehnians</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Ottoman Empire entered this conflict on the eventual losing side during</u></b> <b><u>the Pruth River Campaign. The Treaty of Nystad [[NEE-stad]] allowed the winning</u></b> <b><u>side of this war to seize the land to construct a new capital on the Gulf of (+)</u> Finland. The Battle of Poltava [[pohl-TAH-vuh]] during this conflict ended an invasion of (*) </b>Russia by King Charles XII [[the twelfth]]. For ten points, name this conflict where Russia under Peter the Great ended the golden age of the Swedish Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Great Northern</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A November 2021 prison riot in this nation's</u> </b><em><b><u>Litoral</u></b></em><b><u> Penitentiary led to a call</u></b> <b><u>for a state of emergency by President Guillermo Lasso. Wikileaks founder Julian</u></b> <b><u>Assange (+)</u> was given asylum in this nation's embassy by then-president Rafael Correa [[kor-REH-ah]]. Anti-Lenin Moreno riots led to a government relocation to (*) </b>Guayaquil [[\"why\"-YAH-keel]] in, for ten points, what Andean nation governed from Quito?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Ecuador</u></b> (accept Rep\u00fablica del <b><u>Ecuador</u></b>; or <b><u>Republic of the</u></b> <b><u>Equator</u></b>, accept <b><u>Ikwadur</u></b> Ripuwlika; or <b><u>Chawpipacha</u></b> Ripuwlika; accept <b><u>Ekuatur</u></b> Nunka)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this state, an indoor concert by hair metal band Great White led to a fire in</u></b> <b><u>West Warwick which killed one hundred attendees. In 2015, the governor of this</u></b> <b><u>state proposed a luxury tax on second homes which the media dubbed the \"Taylor</u></b> <b><u>Swift (+)</u> Tax\" due to her having beachfront property there. That governor of this state, Gina Raimondo, resigned to become Joe Biden's Secretary of Commerce. The words \"Providence (*) </b>Plantations\" were dropped from the name of, for ten points, which New England state?", "answer": "<b><u>Rhode Island</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This chemist's mentors included John Ericsson, designer of the U.S.'s first</u></b> <b><u>ironclad, and Ascanio Sobrero, the inventor of nitroglycerin. This man turned the</u></b> <b><u>once royally-owned iron production company Bofors into a cannon manufacturer.</u></b> <b><u>This man was denounced as a (+)</u> war profiteer in an erroneous obituary, leading him to donate his estate to create several (*) </b>namesake awards. For ten points, name this inventor of dynamite, who created a series of prizes awarded by a Swedish foundation.", "answer": "Alfred <b><u>Nobel</u></b> (or Alfred Bernhard <b><u>Nobel</u></b>; accept <b><u>Nobel</u></b> Prize(s); accept <b><u>Nobel</u> </b>Foundation)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}